<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Carnets de notes</title>
    <link>https://jduquesne.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Carnets de notes</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>fr</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Sep 2024 17:12:04 +0800</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://jduquesne.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Stories of Your Life and Others</title>
      <link>https://jduquesne.com/post/livre-stories-ted-chiang/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Sep 2024 17:12:04 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jduquesne.com/post/livre-stories-ted-chiang/</guid>
      
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Ma critique du livre &lt;em&gt;Stories of Your Life and Others&lt;/em&gt; publiée sur &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6885001096&#34;&gt;GoodReads&lt;/a&gt;. Vu que j&amp;rsquo;ai lu le livre en anglais, la revue est en anglais.&lt;/p&gt;











  
  
  
  





  


&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;From 1990 to 2015, Chiang produced just fifteen short stories, eight of which appear in the collection &lt;em&gt;Stories of Your Life and Others&lt;/em&gt;. Within these pages, he showcases remarkable talent and breathtaking concepts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One can easily grasp his lack of prolificacy once engaged with his work. The meticulous way he elaborates on his narratives, almost in a demonstrative fashion, elevates him to the level of the finest writers from his very first collection. It reminded me of my first encounter with Asimov, but with a more inspired prose. Highly recommended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;footer&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Jacques Duquesne&lt;/strong&gt;
    
      
        
      
    
  &lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Piranesi</title>
      <link>https://jduquesne.com/post/livre-piranesi/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 14:39:51 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jduquesne.com/post/livre-piranesi/</guid>
      
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Ma critique du livre &lt;em&gt;Piranesi&lt;/em&gt; publiée sur &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6814336410&#34;&gt;GoodReads&lt;/a&gt; recemment. Je la republie ici pour catalogage et me faciliter la vie. Vu que j&amp;rsquo;ai lu le livre en anglais, la revue est en anglais.&lt;/p&gt;











  
  
  
  





  


&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What a strange and unique novel. Piranesi left me puzzled, and I&amp;rsquo;m still not sure if I loved it or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The atmosphere is incredible—dreamlike and eerie. The line between reality and dream/madness is blurred, making it easy to get lost in the intricate story Susanna Clarke has crafted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The writing alone is worth the read. Though the narrator&amp;rsquo;s naïveté sometimes frustrated me, the beautifully crafted sentences, immersive mood, and intriguing reflections of the protagonist kept me engaged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a curious book—more about the experience than the plot, like navigating a maze. Intriguing and puzzling, it&amp;rsquo;s a journey unlike any other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;footer&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Jacques Duquesne&lt;/strong&gt;
    
      
        
      
    
  &lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Humus</title>
      <link>https://jduquesne.com/post/livre-humus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2024 14:39:59 +0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jduquesne.com/post/livre-humus/</guid>
      
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Ma critique du livre &lt;em&gt;Humus&lt;/em&gt; publiée sur &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/6693623205&#34;&gt;GoodReads&lt;/a&gt; recemment. Je la republie ici pour catalogage et me faciliter la vie.&lt;/p&gt;











  
  
  
  





  


&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Les Lombrics sont un excellent terreau pour explorer une des préoccupations les plus pressantes en France : l&amp;rsquo;écocide de notre planète.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Les deux protagonistes mettent leurs idéaux à l&amp;rsquo;épreuve tout au long du livre. Koenig, en portraitiste talentueux, trouve souvent le mot juste ou la formule lumineuse qui capte l&amp;rsquo;essence d&amp;rsquo;une personnalité ou d&amp;rsquo;une scène. Une histoire de terre et d&amp;rsquo;hommes, avec des echos de Balzac.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cependant, il est regrettable que les personnages féminins principaux soient si frustres et que la fin manque d&amp;rsquo;inspiration. Une longue discussion entre Arthur et Kevin, faisant écho à celle qu&amp;rsquo;ils ont eue les pieds dans l&amp;rsquo;eau, la nuit, en rêvant de leur avenir, aurait été bien plus intéressante.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Un livre qui a pris la poussière sur ma table de chevet bien trop longtemps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;footer&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;Jacques Duquesne&lt;/strong&gt;
    
      
        
      
    
  &lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description>
      
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
